Finding Aid for Elizabeth W. Bauer papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Social Issues
  - Mental Disability and the Law
    - Photographs-Traverse City Regional Psychiatric Hospital, undated (Box 10)
    - Plymouth Center for Human Development, 1978-1997 (Box 10)
    - Southgate Center, 2001 (Box 10)
    - Traverse City Regional Psychiatric Hospital, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Wayne County Eloise Complex, 2000 (Box 10)
    - Winfield State Hospital and Training Center (Bauer consultation), 1997 (Box 10)
    - York Woods Center, 1990 (Box 10)
    - Ypsilanti Regional Psychiatric Hospital, 1987-1990 (Box 10)
    - Americans with Disabilities Act, 1990-1994; 2004-2005 (Box 10)
    - Autism insurance, 2012 (Box 10)
    - Legal rights clips-Ohio, 1969-1974 (Box 10)
    - Legislative correspondence
      - 1970-1980 (Box 10)
      - 1981 (Box 10)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 10)
      - 1983-2001 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Bar Journal, 1987-2001 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Handicappers' Civil Rights Act, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Reports on mental disability cases, 1973-1978; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Reports to the Michigan state legislature, 1976-1978 (Box 10)
    - Wyatt vs. King, 1992 (Box 10)
  - Patient Abuse, 1978-2011
    The Patient Abuse subseries (0.2 linear feet, 1978-2011) details the issue of patient abuse within state institutions and nursing homes in the state of Michigan. This subseries contains reports and newspaper clippings.
    - Guidelines for Assessing Parenting Capabilities in Child Abuse and Neglect Cases, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Joint Committee to Study Abuse in State Mental Health Facilities, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978-2011 (Box 10)
    - Nursing Homes: Abuse and Neglect throughout Michigan, 2011 (Box 10)
    - Staff Report on the Institutionalized Mentally Disabled, 1985 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1963-2013
    The Miscellaneous subseries (0.4 linear feet, 1963-2013) contains materials regarding social issues in mental health and disability rights that do not fit into any of the other subseries. Topics covered in this subseries include disability policy in Michigan, the education of developmentally delayed individuals, mental health issues in Michigan, women and disability, sexuality and people with handicaps, and recreation programs for developmentally delayed persons. This subseries includes newspaper clippings, as well as papers and reports regarding various mental health topics.
    - Disability policy in Michigan, 1990 (Box 10)
    - Education of developmentally delayed, 1969-1986 (Box 10)
    - Effective public policy tactics, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Mensa intelligence testing, 1963-1964 (Box 10)
    - Mental health newspaper clippings, 1979-2013 (Box 11)
    - Opinions of Michigan Citizens: Mental Health Issues, 1990 (Box 11)
    - Poletown, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Promoting Self-Determination through Alternatives to Guardianship, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Recreation programs for developmentally delayed, 1977-1988 (Box 11)
    - Self-Advocacy, 1980-1998 (Box 11)
    - Sexuality and people with handicaps, 1976-1987 (Box 11)
    - Transforming mental health care in Michigan, 2002-2005; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Women and disability, 1997-1999 (Box 11)
- Topical File
  - Action group-education town hall, 2010 (Box 11)
  - Alternative education for expelled students-Jondahl bills, 1991 (Box 11)
  - Alternative education in Michigan, 2004-2008 (Box 11)
  - Anti-Inclusion, 2004
    - Assessment and Training Materials for the Severely Mentally Impaired, 1975; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - The Children and Youth Initiative of Detroit/Wayne County, 1990 (Box 11)
  - Corporal punishment in schools, 1990-1991 (Box 11)
  - Department of Education Special Education Services Investigation Report, 1986 (Box 11)
  - Early on in Michigan: Family Information Exchange Key Player Packet, 2005-2006 (Box 11)
  - Education Development Center materials
    - 1999-2004 (Box 11)
    - Project book, February 27, 2003; .ZIP file
- Education
  The Education series (1.8 linear feet and 70.1 MB, 1958-2013) gives an in-depth picture of education initiatives in Michigan throughout the years, as well as details Bauer's 8 year term serving on the Michigan State Board of Education. Some topics discussed within this series include alternative education, special education services in Michigan, the education of homeless or at-risk youth, inclusive education, Universal Design Learning (UDL), higher education, technology in Michigan schools, intelligent design, and international education. This series contains meeting minutes, reports, surveys, newspaper clippings, newsletters, correspondence, information packets, research papers, CDs, and assessment materials.
  - Education for homeless or at-risk children and youth, 2009-2013 (Box 11)
  - Everyone Together project, 2003-2005 (Box 11)
  - From Teasing to Torment: Report on School Climate in Michigan, 2005 (Box 11)
  - Higher education in Michigan, 2005-2010 (Box 11)
  - ICARE Schools: A Study of Meaningful Parent Involvement in the IEP Process, 2007-2008
    - Inclusive education, 1989-2009; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Inclusive Schools Week
    - 2006-2007 (Box 12)
    - Celebration Kit, 2006; .ZIP file
    - 2009-2011 (Box 12)
    - Intelligent design, 2005-2009; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Intermediate school districts, 2007-2009 (Box 12)
  - International education, 2007-2008 (Box 12)
  - K-12 social studies curriculum, 2007 (Box 12)
  - Leap Inc. Lansing, 2010 (Box 12)
  - Michigan Association of Administrators of Special Education (MAASE), 2008-2009 (Box 12)
  - Michigan Community School Education Association, 1976-1977 (Box 12)
  - Michigan math and science centers, 2006-2009 (Box 12)
  - Michigan school privatization survey, 2008 (Box 12)
  - Michigan teaching materials from, 1958 (Box 12)
  - Mobilizing, Connecting, and Leveraging Michigan's Arts and Cultural Resources to Impact Learning, 2004 (Box 12)
  - Northville Public Schools special education materials, 1977 (Box 12)
  - Oakland Schools universal design for learning
    - 2006-2007 (Box 12)
    - Training Manual, 2006; .ZIP file
  - Pontiac Continuing Education Adult Special Education programs, 1976-1978 (Box 12)
  - Project ReImagine, 2009 (Box 12)
  - Special education in Michigan, 1985, 1990, 2002-2011 (Box 12)
  - State Board of Education correspondence, 2002-2013 (Box 12)
  - State Board of Education executive orders, 1996-2007 (Box 12)
  - State Board of Education school visits and reports, 2006-2010 (Box 12)
  - Technology in Michigan schools, 2005-2010 (Box 13)
  - Universal Design Learning, 2004-2010 (Box 13)
  - Universal Education Referent Group, 2003-2004 (Box 13)
  - Universal Education support letters, 2003-2006 (Box 13)
  - Whole Schooling Consortium, 2003-2006 (Box 13)
  - Wing Lake Student Confrontation Avoidance Techniques program, 1980 (Box 13)
- Conferences and Workshops
  The Conferences and Workshops series (1.8 linear feet, 1971-2012) contains materials relating to the many conferences that Bauer attended over the years, as well as materials regarding workshops that she put on within her work. Topics covered at these conferences include public health, advocacy for developmentally delayed individuals, mental health, disability law, community support services, special education, human sexuality and developmentally delayed persons, and pediatric AIDS, among others. This series contains notes taken by Bauer at the conferences, informational packets about conferences and workshops, and materials covered in conference proceedings.
  - AAMD conventions, 1978-1980 (Box 13)
  - AAMD 106th Annual Meeting-My Community or Elsewhere, 1982 (Box 13)
  - Action Planning Conference on Epilepsy, 1978 (Box 13)
  - Advocacy for case managers workshop, 1989 (Box 13)
  - American Association on Mental Deficiency 110th Annual Meeting, 1986 (Box 13)
  - American Public Health Association conference, 1987 (Box 13)
  - Annual Booth Editorial conference, 1992 (Box 13)
  - Arkansas advocacy conference, 1989 (Box 13)
  - Baby Doe Issues-Advocate's Perspective, 1985 (Box 13)
  - Bovenschen School Parents Association state budget reductions, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Centers for mental health service workshop-Legal and ethical dilemmas in mental health services, 1993 (Box 13)
  - Children's Hospital of Michigan 31st Annual Clinic Days, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Communication: what are we really saying? (Through our behavior), 1988 (Box 13)
  - Community Organization of Parents and Professionals training session, 1989 (Box 13)
  - Community support services: A retrospective and prospective view, 1987 (Box 13)
  - A Conference on the Legal Rights of People with Handicaps--The Attorneys Role with Paralegals, Advocates, and Handicappers Invited, 1984 (Box 13)
  - Consortium of Developmental Disabilities Councils conference, 1998 (Box 13)
  - The Council for Exceptional Children 55th Annual International Convention, 1977 (Box 13)
  - Creating community partnerships for employment of persons with disabilities, 1989 (Box 13)
  - Detroit Public Schools school community relations and special education, 1985 (Box 13)
  - Detroit Public Schools Special Connection II parent workshop, 1985 (Box 13)
  - Disability policy: The state of the nation, 1987 (Box 13)
  - Educating Everyone Together!: 5th Annual Conference on Inclusive Education, 2004 (Box 13)
  - EFA Regional Action on Epilepsy conference, 1978 (Box 13)
  - Embedding character education into the 21st century school, 2009 (Box 13)
  - Foundation for Excellence in Education 2012 National Summit on Education Reform, 2012 (Box 13)
  - Gentle art of teaching, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Gov. Granholm event at Bauer home, 2002 (Box 13)
  - Handicappers in higher education, 1985 (Box 13)
  - How to enable our special needs and Title I students to succeed in the classroom, 2010 (Box 13)
  - Human sexuality-Sex education for exceptional children workshop (Detroit Schools), 1984 (Box 13)
  - Influencing legislation, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Institutionalization of disabled children, 2000 (Box 13)
  - Investing in Healthy People 2000 conference, 1993 (Box 13)
  - Let's talk networking workshop, 1985 (Box 13)
  - Life services: The vision and its history, 1984 (Box 13)
  - MAASE summer institute, 1996 (Box 13)
  - MATEDC conference presentation-Michigan's Protection and Advocacy Service: Role and responsibilities, 1983 (Box 13)
  - MCSEA-MAPACE adult education workshop, 1981 (Box 13)
  - Mental health partnerships and strategies, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Mental Retardation and the Law PCMR conference, 1971-1973 (Box 14)
  - Metzner Careers Center parenting conference-Sexuality, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Michigan Association of Community Mental Health Boards-History of the CMH movement, 1989 (Box 14)
  - Michigan Association of Rehabilitation Facilities Vision of the Future conference, 1989 (Box 14)
  - Michigan Judicial Institute workshop, 1984 (Box 14)
  - Michigan right to choose/right to refuse forum, 1989 (Box 14)
  - Michigan Transition Outcomes Project MTSA pre-conference workshop, 2011 (Box 14)
  - Middle Cities Organization-Special education subcommittee presentation, 1983 (Box 14)
  - MORC conference for group home direct care stuff, 1983 (Box 14)
  - MORC conference-Professionals and natural parents, 1983 (Box 14)
  - NAPAS annual conference-Training for board members workshop, 1989 (Box 14)
  - NASBE's 2012 conference on evidence-based policymaking and innovation, 2012 (Box 14)
  - National Association for Rights Protection and Advocacy 1990 conference, 1990 (Box 14)
  - National Association of Protection and Advocacy director's meeting, 1986 (Box 14)
  - National conference on fair housing and disability, 1995 (Box 14)
  - National Rehabilitation Association conference, 1990 (Box 14)
  - National Symposium on Abuse and Neglect, 1991 (Box 14)
  - National Working Conference on Positive Approaches to the Management of Excess Behavior, 1990 (Box 14)
  - New life in the neighborhood, 1981 (Box 14)
  - Normalization: Do we have it in our homes?, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Nursing practice issues in developmental disabilities: Resolving the dilemma, 1984 (Box 14)
  - Oklahoma Association for Retarded Citizens, Inc. annual convention, 1987-1991 (Box 14)
  - Parent education-Franklin County, 1973-1974 (Box 14)
  - Pediatric AIDS: Legal and service issues workshop, 1989 (Box 14)
  - People First, 1993 (Box 14)
  - Personal advocacy program, 1974 (Box 14)
  - Planting Seeds for the Future conference: American disability laws, 2003 (Box 14)
  - Program analysis of the service systems, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Protection and advocacy as a community resource (MSU), 1984 (Box 14)
  - Rally 'Round Community Placement, 1981 (Box 14)
  - Rights protection issues/resources, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Sexuality-Responding to campers' sexual expression of behavior, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Speaker's Law Day conference, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Special Connection III parent conference, 1986 (Box 14)
  - Special Connection IV parent workshop and luncheon, 1987 (Box 14)
  - Special education funding, 1997 (Box 14)
  - Strategies for strengthening the family: Coping as parents of handicapped children, 1980 (Box 14)
  - Think College: Postsecondary Education for Students with Intellectual Disabilities Symposium, 2007 (Box 14)
  - Transition conference, 2007 (Box 14)
  - Universal access to reading and writing across the curriculum, 2006 (Box 14)
  - Universal Education workshop, 2006 (Box 14)
  - A Very special workshop for professionals and parents of mentally retarded and developmentally disabled children and adults, 1985 (Box 14)
  - White House Conference on the Handicapped, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Women in the courtroom and in the law firm, 1983 (Box 14)
  - 5th Biennial Legislative Conference of the Ohio Association for Retarded Citizens, 1974 (Box 14)
  - 6th International Congress of the International Association for the Scientific Study of Mental Deficiency, 1982 (Box 14)
  - 17th Annual TASH Conference: Action for Inclusion, 1990 (Box 15)
  - The 25th Annual Michigan Rehabilitation conference, 2009 (Box 15)
  - 33rd Annual Conference of the Association for Retarded Citizens/Michigan, 1984 (Box 15)
  - 34th Annual Conference of the Association for Retarded Citizens/Michigan, 1985 (Box 15)
  - 1987 Rights Conference, Rights Not Privileges: Strategies for Advocates, 1987 (Box 15)
- International Consultation
  The International Consultation series (0.5 linear feet, 1986-2004) details the work that Bauer did as a disability and human rights consultant in the Czech Republic, Hungary, and Kosovo. This series contains reports, correspondence, meeting proceedings, training materials, informational packets, and photographs. Some materials within this series are in languages other than English.
  - AADJC-IDP training of trainers report (Prague), 1994 (Box 15)
  - Czech Republic, 1986-2003 (with gaps); 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Hungary, 1995-2002 (Box 15)
  - Kosovo, 2002-2004 (Box 15)
- Speeches and Writings
  The Speeches and Writings series (1.7 linear feet and 8.2 MB, 1973-2010) contains the speeches that Elizabeth Bauer gave over the course of her career as a disability rights advocate and as a member of the Michigan State Board of Education, in addition to the writings and publications that she has produced over the years. Topics discussed within this series include: parenting children with epilepsy, bringing about change at the facility and community level, parent-professional relationships, advocacy challenges, disability rights, communities in schools, achieving independence with disability, special education, and the role of the government in the delivery of mental health services, among others.
  - AAMD Michigan chapter-Parent/professional relationships, 1982 (Box 15)
  - AAMD speeches-Why Training and the State of the Agency in the Context of Planned Change theory, 1981 (Box 15)
  - Accreditation, 1978 (Box 15)
  - Achieving Independence: The Challenge for the 21st Century, National Council on Disability, 1996 (Box 15)
  - Action Day conferences, 2002; 2006 (Box 15)
  - Advocacy Challenges in the 90s, 1990 (Box 15)
  - Advocacy Skills for Professionals and Parents in Early Intervention Programs, 1991 (Box 15)
  - A.H.S. Success Day, 1989 (Box 15)
  - Bringing about Micro-System Change: Change Agency Applied at the Facility and Community Level, 1980 (Box 15)
  - Building Bridges to Facilitate Positive Changes, 1997 (Box 15)
  - Bureaucratic and Professional Aspects of the Formal Organization of Schools, 1973 (Box 15)
  - Buying the Basics: Food and Clothing, 1974 (Box 15)
  - Cadillac-Missaukee RICC Annual Dinner keynote, 1989 (Box 15)
  - Caregiver appreciation luncheon, 2001 (Box 15)
  - Children and Families at Risk, 1985 (Box 15)
  - Citizen Advocacy Awards Dinner, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Clients Rights conferences, 1997; 2002 (Box 15)
  - CMH Boards Association Banquet, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Communities in Schools, 2009 (Box 15)
  - Controversial Land Uses seminar, 1984 (Box 16)
  - Council for Exceptional Children convention presentation, 1977-1978 (Box 16)
  - Department of Mental Health director's presentation, undated (Box 16)
  - EACH, Inc. Annual Conference Luncheon address, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Editorial in Detroit Free Press re. tax increase, 1983-1984 (Box 16)
  - Educational Program of Maria Montessori, 1974 (Box 16)
  - Everyone Together Oakland County catch the spirit contest, 2005 (Box 16)
  - Expanding Your Practice to Include People with Disabilities, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Foster parent recognition day, 1986 (Box 16)
  - History of Community-based Services, 1988 (Box 16)
  - How to Advocate, 1987 (Box 16)
  - Human Resource Development: The Keystone of Quality Care, 1987 (Box 16)
  - Implementing the Right to Community Integration for Children with Disabilities in Russia: A Human Rights Framework for International Action, 1999 (Box 16)
  - Indus Council of Academic Excellence, 2005 (Box 16)
  - Interdependent Living Council of Michigan-We're Making It on Our Own, 1987 (Box 16)
  - Interview with Elizabeth Bauer in Wayne Community Living Services newsletter Frontline, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Investing in People: Meeting Mental Health Needs, Living and Working in the Community, A Rally at the Capitol, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Issues on Advocacy: Where You Fit In, 1990 (Box 16)
  - It's Worth the Time, 1991 (Box 16)
  - Kalamazoo ARC Awards Banquet-On Valuing People, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Kenny Michigan Rehabilitation Foundation annual meeting, 1987 (Box 16)
  - Keynote address First Annual Disability Rights Bar Association conference, 1991 (Box 16)
  - Keynote address: Innovative Integration, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Keynote address: Legal Rights of Handicapped conference (Western Michigan University), 1982 (Box 16)
  - Keynote to Community Providers Dinner, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Kiwanis address, 1988 (Box 16)
  - Language assessment activities, 1974 (Box 16)
  - Language Shapes Ideas, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Lay-off and Recall Procedures, 1978 (Box 16)
  - Leap article, 2010 (Box 16)
  - Legal Issues and Epilepsy, 1984 (Box 16)
  - Macomb Oakland Regional Center lecture series-Michigan perspective, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Making Change game, undated (Box 16)
  - Maternal and Child Health Leadership conference, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Michigan After-school Collaborative conference, 2006 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Commission on Handicapped Concerns speech, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Council Teachers of English conference luncheon address, 2007 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Developmental Disabilities Council, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Judicial Institute speech, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Oklahoma Governor's Conference on Developmental Disabilities, 1998 (Box 16)
  - NAPAS president speeches, 1992-1993 (Box 16)
  - Notes on "Introduction to Mental Retardation", undated (Box 16)
  - Notes on Psychology course, 1974 (Box 16)
  - P and A Past and Present, with a Focus on the Future, 1982 (Box 16)
  - PARC/AMORC rally, 1991 (Box 16)
  - Parent network program in service, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Parents Speak to the Professionals: The Family's View of the Child with Special Health Care Needs, 1987 (Box 16)
  - Partnership and Participation-Keys to Quality Services in the, 1990s; 1990 (Box 16)
  - People First conference banquet speeches, 1982-1983 (Box 16)
  - People First of Michigan "Understanding Our Legislature", 1982 (Box 16)
  - Perspectives on Advocacy-Speech to Oklahoma City Parent Providers, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Presentation on deinstitutionalization, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Project: Self Sufficiency (Pontiac Public Schools Continuing Education Department), 1977 (Box 16)
  - Protection and Advocacy for Mentally Ill Individuals Act (NAPAS' recommendations), undated (Box 17)
  - Protection of the Disabled Subject, 1991 (Box 17)
  - Response to Intervention speech, 2007 (Box 17)
  - A Review of the Life and Teachings of Dr. Maria Montessori, 1974 (Box 17)
  - Robert Scott Correctional Facility, 2005 (Box 17)
  - Role of government in delivery of mental health service speech, 1999 (Box 17)
  - A Silent Minority Speak Up, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Special education rally, 2007 (Box 17)
  - Speech to parents-Hissom Memorial Center, 1989 (Box 17)
  - Taylor School District opening day convocation, 2003 (Box 17)
  - Testimonial to Mike Vennum, undated (Box 17)
  - Testimonies of Elizabeth Bauer, 1988-2001 (Box 17)
  - Third Annual Conference Developmental Disabilities-Advocacy through Clinical Excellence, 1987 (Box 17)
  - Thoughts on Advocacy-Or How to Become an Effective Change Agent, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Thoughts on Parenting the Child with Epilepsy, 1977 (Box 17)
  - Transforming Instruction and Enhancing Student Learning through Technology, 2004 (Box 17)
  - Transforming Systems of Care through Human Rights Investigations and Advocacy
    - Presentation and conference materials, 2007 (Box 17)
    - Presentation slides, 2007; .ZIP file
  - United Cerebral Palsy Association of Metro Detroit, Inc. annual meeting, 1988 (Box 17)
  - Universal Design for Learning speech, undated (Box 17)
  - Universal Education: A Framework for Educational Policy Development in Michigan, 2006 (Box 17)
  - We Can II: 2nd annual self-advocacy conference, 1991 (Box 17)
  - Western District Adult Education commencement, 2008 (Box 17)
  - Winning Futures Receives Kudos from State School Board Member, 2010 (Box 17)
  - Year's Plan of Work, 1974 (Box 17)
  - Your Role and responsibility in the Fiscal Year 1989 Executive Budget and Appropriations Process, 1989 (Box 17)
  - 4th Annual Family Support Forum for Special Needs Children and Adults, 1988 (Box 17)
  - 8th Annual AT&T-MACUL Student Technology Showcase, 2005 (Box 17)
  - Breaking Traditions Awards presentation, 2008 (Box 17)